A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation [DRAFT], 2018-2021.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation,
2018-2021.
The Library of Virginia
53529
Virginia. Secretary of Transportation.
4.45 cu. ft. (14 boxes)
Administrative Information
Arranged by series.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions
Acquisition Information
Accession 53529 was transferred by the Secretary of Transportation Jan 7, 2022.
Historical Information
In 1970 the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The Office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Shannon Valentine served as Secretary of Transportation during the administration of Governor Ralph Northam. As Secretary, she also serves as Chair of the Commonwealth Transportation Board (CTB). Valentine previously served in the Virginia House of Delegates, 2006-2009, and as a member of the Virginia Commonwealth Transportation Board for the Lynchburg District. She graduated Phi Beta Kappa from the University of Virginia in economics.
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Transportation records, 2018-2021, consist of 14 archival boxes and are divided into 8 series. Series have been designated for Correspondence - Assigned State Agencies (I), Correspondence - Constituent (II), Correspondence - Secretary (III), Commonwealth Transportation Board (IV), Governor Decision Requests (V), Subject files (VI), Files of Quintin Elliott, Dep. Sec. of Transportation (VII) and Files of John Lawson, Dep. Sec. of Transportation (VIII). These records document the work of Secretary of Transportation Shannon Valentaine during the Northam administration and were created or collected, 2018-2021, though some documents in this collection pre-date this time period.
Contents List
- Records of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 2018-2021.
  - Series I: Correspondence: Correspondence with Assigned State Agencies, 2018-2021., Extent: .5 cu. ft.
    Correspondence with Assigned State Agencies, 2018-2021, is housed in 2 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by agency name. Includes correspondence with the following agencies: Dept. of Aviation (DOAV), Dept. of Motor Vehicles (DMV), Dept. of Rail and Public Transportation (DRPT), Dept. of Transportation (VDOT) and the Virginia Port Authority (VPA). Includes both incoming correspondence and copies of outgoing correspondence with state, federal and local agencies and officials; state and federal legislators; and associations. In addition to correspondence, may also include decision briefs and reports. Topics include, but are not limited to: airports, bridge projects, Chesapeake Bay Bridge and tunnels, funding, higway and rail safety, Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority (MWAA), passenger rail expansion, Port of Virginia, Transportation Safety Grants, and the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority (WMATA).
    - Aviation, Dept. of, 2018-2019. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Aviation, Dept. of, 2020-2021. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of, 2018. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of, 2019. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of, 2020-2021. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of - Approval of the Federal Fiscal Year 2019 Transportation Safety Grant Funding Recommendations, 2018. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of - Approval of the Federal Fiscal Year 2022 Transportation Safety Grant Funding Recommendations, 2020. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of - Driver's License Suspension for Non-Payment of Court Fines and Costs, 2018. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of, 2018-2019. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of, 2020-2021. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of - Annual Status Report on Rail Fixed Guideway State Safety Oversight and Program Performance (2017), 2018. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of - Intercity Passenger Rail Service (Bedford, Va.), 2016-2019. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of - Report on the Performance and Condition of the Washington Metropolitan Area Transportation Authority (by the Northern Virginia Transportation Commission), 2019. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of - Transform 66 Inside the Beltway Project MOA, undated. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of - Virginia's 21st Century Rail Development Program, 2018. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Transportation, Dept. of, 2018. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Transportation, Dept. of, 2019. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Transportation, Dept. of, 2020. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Transportation, Dept. of - Chesapeake Bay Bridge and Tunnel District Annual Report, 2019. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Transportation, Dept. of - Transportation Action Plan, 2020 Jan. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Port Authority, 2018-2021. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Virginia Port Authority - The Port of Virginia Strategic Growth Plan (2016-2018), 2016. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Series II: Correspondence: Constituent correspondence, 2018-2021., Extent: .35 cu. ft.
    Constituent correspondence, 2018-2021, is housed in 1 box and is arranged chronologically. Includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence, as well as drafts of outgoing correspondence. Topics may include, but are not limited to: autonomous vehicles, DMV issues, drainage issues, environmental concerns, express lanes, high speed rail, rail transportation, road construction and maintenance, road safety, tolls, traffic congestion, and tunnels. Series is not complete.
    - Incoming correspondence, 2018. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Incoming correspondence, 2019. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Incoming correspondence, 2020. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Incoming correspondence, 2021. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 2018 Apr. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 2018 May. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 2018 June. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 2018 July. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 2018 Aug-Sept. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Outgoing correspondence, 2021. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Series III: Correspondence: Correspondence of the Secretary, 2018-2021., Extent: .35 cu. ft.
    Correspondence of the Secretary, 2018-2021, is housed in 1 box and is arranged chronologically. Includes copies of outgoing correspondence and some incoming correspondence with associations, businesses, federal government (Federal Highway Administration, US Dept. of Transportation), legislators, local government (mayors, boards of supervisors), organizations, and regional transportation commissions. May also include invitations and reports. Topics include, but are not limited to: Better Utilizing Investments to Leverage Development (BUILD) funds, Elizabeth River Tunnels, funding, Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel, legislation, Six Year Improvement Plan (SYIP), Smart Scale, State Environmental Review Process (SERP), Statewide Transportation Improvement Plan (STIP), transportation infrastructure, Transportation Partnership Opportunity Fund, and the Virginia Museum of Transportation.
    - Correspondence, 2018 Feb-June. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2018 July-Dec. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 2019 Jan-June. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2019 July-Dec. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 2020 Jan-June. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 2020 July-Dec. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 2021 Jan-Apr. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2021 May-Nov. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, undated. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Series IV: Commonwealth Transportation Board, 2018-2021., Extent: .35 cu. ft. (1 box)
    Commonwealth Transportation Board (CTB) records, 2018-2021, are housed in 1 box and are arranged alphabetically. Records include incoming correspondence and a small amount of outgoing correspondence, with contractors, the Governor's Office, localities, regional transporation organizations, legislators, and the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority. Also includes meeting records (agendas, briefs, presentations, resolutions) for the 2018 July 17-18 meeting of the Commonwealth Transportation Board; and a CTB Handbook, 2018. Topics include, but are not limited to: Interstate Corridor Improvement Plan, public meetings, Six Year Improvement Plan (SYIP), Smart Scale, tolls, and Transportation Revenue Refunding Bonds.
    - Correspondence, 2018-2019. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 2020-2021. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Handbook, 2018 June. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Meeting, 2018 July 17. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Meeting, 2018 July 18. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Richmond Highway, 2019. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Transportation Revenue Refunding Bonds, 2019. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Series V: Governor Decision Requests, 2018-2021., Extent: 1.05 cu. ft. (4 boxes)
    Governor Decision Requests, 2018-2021, are housed in 4 boxes and are arranged chronologically. This series documents requests sent to the Governor for his approval and may include background information with discussion and summary, as well as tracking sheets, recommendations, comments and signatures. Supplemental information may include correspondence, drafts and reports. Many of the requests are for approval to send letters or to submit reports and studies to the General Assembly, permission to travel on the state plane, or requests for the Governor's signature on correspondence. Topics include, but are not limited to: grant applications, infrastructure, Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority (MWAA) bonds, Passenger Rail Investment and Improvement Act, rail transportation, Real ID, Virginia Port Authority, and the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority (WMATA). These requests are also often referred to as Gold Sheets.
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Feb-Apr. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 May. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 June. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 July. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Aug. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Sept. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Oct. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Oct 26. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 nov 7-8. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Nov 9. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Nov 13. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Nov 20-29. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2018 Dec. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Jan 2-4. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Jan 8-Feb 21. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Mar. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Apr. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 May. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 June. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 July. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Aug. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Sept. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Oct. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Nov. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Dec 9. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Dec 9. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Dec 13-17. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2019 Dec 20-23. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2020 Jan-Feb. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2020 Mar-May. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2020 June. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2020 July-Sept. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2020 Oct-Dec. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2021 Jan-Feb. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2021 Mar. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2021 Apr. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2021 May-July. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2021 Aug-Sept. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Governor Decision Requests, 2021 Oct-Nov. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Series VI: Subject files, 2018-2021., Extent: .9 cu. ft.
    Subject files, 2018-2021, are housed in 3 boxes and are arranged alphabetically. These topical files include correspondence, correspondence with state agencies, financial statements, plans, and reports. Topics covered include, but are not limited to: CARES Act, Elizabeth River Crossings, Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel, hiring freeze, Northern Virginia Transportation Commission, strategic planning, succession planning, and the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority.
    - Attorney General's Office, 2015, 2018, undated. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - CARES Act, 2020. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Clean Fleet Action Plan, 2021. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - CRM, 2018. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Elizabeth River Crossings, 2020. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Elizabeth River Crossings - Task Force, 2011. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Emergency Management, Dept. of, 2018. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Financial statements, 2018. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Financial statements, 2019. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Financial statements, 2020. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Financial statements, 2021. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Governor, Office of the, 2018. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel - Bird Report (Part I), 2018. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel - Bird Report (Part II), 2018. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel - Tern colony, 2019-2020. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Hiring Freeze, 2020. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Intermodal Planning and Investment, Office of, 2019-2020. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 2019-2020. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Norfolk's St. Paul Community, undated. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Northern Virginia Transportation Commission, 2018-2020. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Public hearing requirements, 2018. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - State Inspector General, 2018. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Strategic planning, undated. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Succession plans, 2018. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Series VII: Files of Quintin Elliott, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, 2018., Extent: .9 cu. ft. (3 boxes)
    Files of Quintin Elliott, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, 2018, are housed in 3 boxes and are arranged alphabetically. These files include correspondence, correspondence with state agencies, agendas, briefs, charts, plans, presentations, reports, studies, talking points, and topical files. Topics include, but are not limited to: Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel, interstate and highway construction and maintenance, Smart Scale, strategic planning, and succession planning. Quintin Elliot was appointed Deputy Secretary in January 2018 and had previously served Chief Deputy Commissioner of the Virginia Dept. of Transportation.
    - Assistant Secretary of Transportation - Responsibilities, undated. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Economic Development Projects, 2018. (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Energy Services Company (ESCO) - LED Roadway Lighting, 2017-2018. (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - General Assembly, 2018. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel, 2017-2018. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Hampton Roads Transportation Accountability Commission (HRTAC), 2018. (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Hampton Roads Transportation Accountability Commission (HRTAC) - Funding, 2018. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Highway Safety, 2018. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Interstate 64, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Interstate 66, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Interstate 81 - Corridor Improvement Plan, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Motor Vehicles, Dept. of, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Natural Resources - Climate, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Norris Bridge, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Northern Virginia Transportation Investment, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Port of Virginia, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Rail and Public Transportation, Dept. of - CSX, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Resilience, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Route 29, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Route 58 (Salem), 2018. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Route 460 - Coalfields Expressway, 2018. (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Smart Scale, 2018. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Strategic priorities and goals, 2018. (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Succession planning, 2018. (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Transportation, Dept. of, 2018. (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Transportation, Dept. of - Maintenance Performance, 2018. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Series VIII: Files of John Lawson, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, 2019-2021., Extent: .45 cu. ft. (1 box)
    Files of John Lawson, 2019-2021, are housed in 1 box and are arranged alphabetically. These files include meeting notes, presentations, reports and topical files. John Lawson was appointed Deputy Secretary in April 2019 and had previously served as the Chief Financial Officer of the Virginia Dept. of Transportation since 2010.
    - Dulles Greenway, 2019. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Elizabeth River Crossings, 2019. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Fiber optics, 2019. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Funding, 2019. (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Innovation updates, 2019. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Interstate 81, 2019. (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Meeting notes, 2019 Apr-Aug. (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Meeting notes, 2019 Aug-2020 Feb. (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Meeting notes, 2020 Feb-Aug. (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Meeting notes, 2020 Aug-2021 Dec. (Box 14, Folder 10)